A Guide to the Stuart Circle Hospital records
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Stuart Circle Hospital records 1913 - 1992
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
2001/Nov/11
1.42 linear feet, 2 collection boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This Collection was donated by Dr. Wyatt S. Beazley III.
Biographical/Historical Information
Stuart Circle Hospital opened in 1913. The location, at the beginning of Monument Ave, near the J.E.B. Stuart statute, was chosen for its quiet and peaceful vistas. Stuart Circle was opened by seven Richmond doctors who felt that a more individual approach to medicine would be better for their patients. These doctors, led by Dr. Lewis C. Bosher, formed the hospitals first board of directors.
Designed by Charles M. Robinson, a prolific designer of public buildings in Virginia, the hospital was a six story red brick building. Much of the sixth floor was dedicated to a large roof garden. Each floor had a solarium, a prominent feature of many hospitals built during this time, where patients could relax in what was thought of as the healing rays of the sun. The hospital was constructed with marble and tile floors, high ceilings, and large stairways to allow for more natural light.
Stuart Circle was deemed a closed staff hospital, meaning that the doctors worked amongst themselves. This gave the hospital a feeling of familiarity. All of the doctors were members of the board of directors, so they all had equal standing in administering the hospital. In 1928, the board grew from its initial seven members to ten, only adding doctors when a vacancy was created. The board created Stuart Circle Hospital, Inc. and this body controlled the hospital until they joined Charter Medical Corporation in 1975. Stuart Circle's board was able to maintain its autonomy even after the merger.
Changes to the building were necessary as the hospital grew. By 1943, the roof garden and solariums had to be converted to patient rooms. In 1964, a new addition was built along the eastern side and was known as the "new wing." In 1978, after an attempt to move the hospital to Bon Air in Chesterfield County, the hospital underwent a major renovation, bringing the total number of patient beds to over 150, and adding a parking facility.
Stuart Circle was known for its innovations. In 1977, it started a pilot program and became one of the first hospitals to experiment with same-day surgery, as an alternative to hospital stays and their added expenses. It was the first hospital in Virginia to perform echocardiograms, and was known as a leader in advanced heart care. Stuart Circle also established a program for the deaf via a video tape explaining hospital procedures and policies, and was one of the first to champion the idea of patient education in healthcare.
Stuart Circle had a School of Nursing from 1914 to 1975. During those years it graduated 1,063 nurses. After 1928, it was affiliated with the Richmond Professional Institute and later, Virginia Commonwealth University. The nursing students were now able to use their training at Stuart Circle to earn their bachelor's degree. One of its most distinguished directors was Charlotte Pfeiffer, RN who served on the Virginia Board of Nursing from 1926-1936. She was also the President of the Virginia Nurses' Association from 1940-1942.
By 2000, the hospital was closed. The building underwent renovation and became luxury apartments named One Monument Ave.
Scope and Content
This collections most prominent feature includes several hardbound copies of the Minutes of the Board of Directors dated from 1946-1970. Also included are photographs and newspaper clippings regarding the hospital that appeared in the Richmond Times-Dispatch or News Leader. Due to the fact these were the few records that were saved at the time of the hospital's closure, the collection is missing more detailed information regarding the School of Nursing, and the daily operation of the hospital and its staff.
Arrangement
Records are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Stuart Circle Hospital official papers, 1946-1985
  - Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1946-1970, Bound Volumes
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1960 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1964 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1965 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1968 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Advisory Panel Report, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Other Records
    - Budget and statistical report, 1985 (Box-folder 2:1)
      Photocopy of the original computer printout.
- Hospital Printed Material and History
  - "History of Stuart Circle Hospital," 21 November 1984 (Box-folder 2:2)
    A history of the hospital written by Jerome Caudle.
  - School of Nursing, Stuart Circle Hospital, Twenty-Fifth Anniversary booklet, 1938 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Biography of the Simmons twins, 1992 (Box-folder 2:2)
    Autobiographic statement from the first twins born at the Hospital on May 7, 1914.
  - Hospital bill, 19 October 1930 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Notes (Box-folder 2:2)
    Handwritten slips of paper related to the stock purchase. Found within several volumes of the bound minutes.
  - OccuMed folder (Box-folder 2:3)
    This folder contains information on the hospital's Occupational Medicine Services.
  - Diabetic Treatment Program (Box-folder 2:3)
    Flyer highlighting the hospital's inpatient and outpatient diabetic program.
  - Color Me Well coloring book. (Box-folder 2:3)
    This coloring book made from pen and ink drawings was given to children as they came to the hospital. The artwork and story were created by hospital staff.
  - Preparations for the EEG (Box-folder 2:3)
    A pad of paper with information and maps concerning patients necessary preparations for an EEG.
  - Patient Information pamphlet. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Useful information regarding hospital rules and procedures.
- Newspaper Clippings of the Stuart Circle Hospital, 1973-1991, Newspaper clippings both mounted and unmounted.
  This series contains clippings related to the hospital and its staff. Almost all articles from the Richmond Times-Dispatch and News Leader.
  - 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - 1975 (Box-folder 2:5)
    Demotion of Westbrook Plantation, closing of the Nursing School at Stuart Circle.
  - 1976 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - 1977 (Box-folder 2:7)
    Hospital construction plans.
  - 1978 (Box-folder 2:8)
    Construction completed.
  - 1979 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - 1980 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - 1981 (Box-folder 2:11)
    State Senator Edward Willey's heart attack.
  - 1982, 1984 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:13)
    Financial woes of hospital's parent company.
- Photographs of the Stuart Circle Hospital
  This series contains photographs of the hospital and its staff.
  - Stuart Circle Hospital, circa 1928 (Box-folder 2:14)
    This folder contains photographs of the interior of the hospital as well as some in the outdoor courtyard.
  - Stuart Circle Hospital, circa 1987 (Box-folder 2:15)
    This folder contains photographs of the hospital workers on duty along with several of the exterior of the hospital.
  - School of Nursing, undated, 1948, 1954 (Box-folder 2:16)
    This folder contains photographs of the School of Nursing along with interiors of the Laurel Hill House that was used as a dormitory after 1931. Also includes photographs of candlelight ceremony and the class of 1954.
  - Portrait photographs (Box-folder 2:17)
    This folder contains the photographic portraits of several important doctors at Stuart Circle. Included are Greer Baughman, Lewis C. Bosher, Robert S. Bosher, Jr., Robert C. Bryan, Benjamin H. Gray, Fred M. Hodges, William L. Mason, Jr., Clifton M. Miller, Charlotte Pfeiffer, William D.Suggs and Robert H. Wright. Also includes a portrait of Mary Grace Scherer Taylor.
  - Construction photos, 1978 (Box-folder 2:18)
    This folder contains photographs of the foundation construction of the most recent expansion of the hospital.
  - Miscellaneous Photographs (Box-folder 2:19)
    This folder contains photographs of the opening of a private medical practice as well as a three generation photograph. All photographs are unmarked and undated.
  - Images of Stuart Circle Hospital, oversize (Box 1)
    This folder contains a large photograph, an etching with negative, and a drawing of the hospital.
  - Negatives and photographic proof sheets. (Box-folder 2:20)
  - Color Slides (Box-folder 2:21)
    Slides of the exterior of the hospital as well as several nurses.